<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY % all.entities SYSTEM "all-entities.ent">
%all.entities;
]>
<chapter id="installation">

  <title>Installation Details</title>

  <para>
    As installation of VirtualBox varies depending on your host
    operating system, we provide installation instructions in four
    separate chapters for Windows, Mac OS X, Linux and Solaris,
    respectively.
  </para>

  <sect1 id="installation_windows">

    <title>Installing on Windows Hosts</title>

    <sect2 id="install-win-prereq">

      <title>Prerequisites</title>

      <para>
        For the various versions of Windows that are supported as host
        operating systems, please refer to
        <xref
      linkend="hostossupport" />.
      </para>

      <para>
        In addition, Windows Installer 1.1 or higher must be present on
        your system. This should be the case if you have all recent
        Windows updates installed.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="install-win-performing">

      <title>Performing the Installation</title>

      <para>
        The VirtualBox installation can be started in either of the
        following ways:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            By double-clicking on the executable file, which contains
            both 32-bit and 64-bit architectures.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            By entering the following command:
          </para>

<screen>VirtualBox-&lt;version&gt;-&lt;revision&gt;-Win.exe -extract</screen>

          <para>
            This will extract both installers into a temporary
            directory, along with .MSI files. Run the following command
            to to perform the installation:
          </para>

<screen>msiexec /i VirtualBox-&lt;version&gt;-&lt;revision&gt;-MultiArch_&lt;x86|amd64&gt;.msi</screen>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        Using either way displays the installation Welcome dialog and
        enables you to choose where to install VirtualBox, and which
        components to install. In addition to the VirtualBox
        application, the following components are available:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">USB support.</emphasis> This package
            contains special drivers for your Windows host that
            VirtualBox requires to fully support USB devices inside your
            virtual machines.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Networking.</emphasis> This package
            contains extra networking drivers for your Windows host that
            VirtualBox needs to support Bridged Networking. This enables
            your VM's virtual network cards to be accessed from other
            machines on your physical network.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Python support.</emphasis> This
            package contains Python scripting support for the VirtualBox
            API, see <xref linkend="VirtualBoxAPI" />. For this to work,
            an already working Windows Python installation on the system
            is required.
          </para>

          <para>
            See, for example:
            <ulink
              url="http://www.python.org/download/windows/">http://www.python.org/download/windows/</ulink>.
          </para>

          <note>
            <para>
              Python version at least 2.6 is required. Since VirtualBox
              5.1, Python 3 is also supported.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        Depending on your Windows configuration, you may see warnings
        about unsigned drivers, or similar. Click
        <emphasis role="bold">Continue</emphasis> for these warnings, as
        otherwise VirtualBox might not function correctly after
        installation.
      </para>

      <para>
        The installer will create a VirtualBox group in the Windows
        Start menu, which allows you to launch the application and
        access its documentation.
      </para>

      <para>
        With standard settings, VirtualBox will be installed for all
        users on the local system. If this is not wanted, you must
        invoke the installer by first extracting as follows:
      </para>

<screen>VirtualBox.exe -extract</screen>

      <para>
        Then, run either of the following commands on the extracted .MSI
        files. This will install VirtualBox only for the current user.
      </para>

<screen>VirtualBox.exe -msiparams ALLUSERS=2</screen>

<screen>msiexec /i VirtualBox-&lt;version&gt;-MultiArch_&lt;x86|amd64&gt;.msi ALLUSERS=2</screen>

      <para>
        If you do not want to install all features of VirtualBox, you
        can set the optional <computeroutput>ADDLOCAL</computeroutput>
        parameter to explicitly name the features to be installed. The
        following features are available:
      </para>

      <variablelist>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            VBoxApplication
          </term>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              Main binaries of VirtualBox.

              <note>
                <para>
                  This feature must not be absent, since it contains the
                  minimum set of files to have working VirtualBox
                  installation.
                </para>
              </note>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            VBoxUSB
          </term>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              USB support.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            VBoxNetwork
          </term>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              All networking support. This includes the VBoxNetworkFlt
              and VBoxNetworkAdp features.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            VBoxNetworkFlt
          </term>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              Bridged networking support.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            VBoxNetworkAdp
          </term>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              Host-only networking support
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            VBoxPython
          </term>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              Python support
            </para>

            <note>
              <para>
                Python version at least 2.6 is required. Since
                VirtualBox 5.1, Python 3 is also supported.
              </para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>

      <para>
        For example, to only install USB support along with the main
        binaries, run either of the following commands:
      </para>

<screen>VirtualBox.exe -msiparams ADDLOCAL=VBoxApplication,VBoxUSB</screen>

<screen>msiexec /i VirtualBox-&lt;version&gt;-MultiArch_&lt;x86|amd64&gt;.msi ADDLOCAL=VBoxApplication,VBoxUSB</screen>

      <para>
        The user is able to choose between NDIS5 and NDIS6 host network
        filter drivers during the installation. This is done using a
        command line parameter,
        <computeroutput>NETWORKTYPE</computeroutput>. The NDIS6 driver
        is default for Windows Vista and later. For older Windows
        versions, the installer will automatically select the NDIS5
        driver and this cannot be changed. For Windows Vista and later
        the user can force an install of the legacy NDIS5 host network
        filter driver by using
        <computeroutput>NETWORKTYPE=NDIS5</computeroutput>. For example,
        to install the NDIS5 driver on Windows 7 use either of the
        following commands:
      </para>

<screen>VirtualBox.exe -msiparams NETWORKTYPE=NDIS5</screen>

<screen>msiexec /i VirtualBox-&lt;version&gt;-MultiArch_&lt;x86|amd64&gt;.msi NETWORKTYPE=NDIS5</screen>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="install-win-uninstall">

      <title>Uninstallation</title>

      <para>
        As VirtualBox uses the standard Microsoft Windows installer,
        VirtualBox can be safely uninstalled at any time. Click the
        program entry in the <emphasis role="bold">Add/Remove
        Programs</emphasis> list in the Windows Control Panel.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="install-win-unattended">

      <title>Unattended Installation</title>

      <para>
        Unattended installations can be performed using the standard MSI
        support.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="install-win-public-props">

      <title>Public Properties</title>

      <para>
        Public properties can be specified via MSI API, to control
        additional behavior and features of the Windows host installer.
        Use either of the following commands:
      </para>

<screen>VirtualBox.exe -msiparams NAME=VALUE [...]</screen>

<screen>msiexec /i VirtualBox-&lt;version&gt;-MultiArch_&lt;x86|amd64&gt;.msi NAME=VALUE [...]</screen>

      <para>
        The following public properties are available.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            VBOX_INSTALLDESKTOPSHORTCUT
          </para>

          <para>
            Specifies whether or not a VirtualBox icon on the desktop
            should be created.
          </para>

          <para>
            Set to <computeroutput>1</computeroutput> to enable,
            <computeroutput>0</computeroutput> to disable. Default is 1.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            VBOX_INSTALLQUICKLAUNCHSHORTCUT
          </para>

          <para>
            Specifies whether or not a VirtualBox icon in the Quick
            Launch Bar should be created.
          </para>

          <para>
            Set to <computeroutput>1</computeroutput> to enable,
            <computeroutput>0</computeroutput> to disable. Default is 1.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            VBOX_REGISTERFILEEXTENSIONS
          </para>

          <para>
            Specifies whether or not the file extensions .vbox,
            .vbox-extpack, .ovf, .ova, .vdi, .vmdk, .vhd and .vdd should
            be associated with VirtualBox. Files of these types then
            will be opened with VirtualBox.
          </para>

          <para>
            Set to <computeroutput>1</computeroutput> to enable,
            <computeroutput>0</computeroutput> to disable. Default is 1.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            VBOX_START
          </para>

          <para>
            Specifies whether or not VirtualBox should be started right
            after successful installation.
          </para>

          <para>
            Set to <computeroutput>1</computeroutput> to enable,
            <computeroutput>0</computeroutput> to disable. Default is 1.
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="installation-mac">

    <title>Installing on Mac OS X Hosts</title>

    <sect2 id="install-mac-performing">

      <title>Performing the Installation</title>

      <para>
        For Mac OS X hosts, VirtualBox ships in a disk image
        (<computeroutput>dmg</computeroutput>) file. Perform the
        following steps to install on a Mac OS X host:
      </para>

      <orderedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Double-click on the <computeroutput>dmg</computeroutput>
            file, to mount the contents.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            A window opens, prompting you to double-click on the
            <computeroutput>VirtualBox.pkg</computeroutput> installer
            file displayed in that window.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            This will start the installer, which allows you to select
            where to install VirtualBox.
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </orderedlist>

      <para>
        After installation, you can find a VirtualBox icon in the
        "Applications" folder in the Finder.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="install-mac-uninstall">

      <title>Uninstallation</title>

      <para>
        To uninstall VirtualBox, open the disk image
        <computeroutput>dmg</computeroutput> file and double-click on
        the uninstall icon shown.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="install-mac-unattended">

      <title>Unattended Installation</title>

      <para>
        To perform a non-interactive installation of VirtualBox you can
        use the command line version of the installer application.
      </para>

      <para>
        Mount the disk image (<computeroutput>dmg</computeroutput>)
        file, as described in the installation procedure, or use the
        following command line:
      </para>

<screen>hdiutil attach /path/to/VirtualBox-xyz.dmg</screen>

      <para>
        Open a terminal session and run the following command:
      </para>

<screen>sudo installer -pkg /Volumes/VirtualBox/VirtualBox.pkg -target /Volumes/Macintosh\ HD</screen>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="install-linux-host">

    <title>Installing on Linux Hosts</title>

    <sect2 id="install-linux-prereq">

      <title>Prerequisites</title>

      <para>
        For the various versions of Linux that are supported as host
        operating systems, see <xref
      linkend="hostossupport" />.
      </para>

      <para>
        You will need to install the following packages on your Linux
        system before starting the installation. Some systems will do
        this for you automatically when you install VirtualBox.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Qt 5.3.2 or higher. Qt 5.6.2 or higher is recommended.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            SDL 1.2.7 or higher. This graphics library is typically
            called <computeroutput>libsdl</computeroutput> or similar.
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <note>
        <para>
          These packages are only required if you want to run the
          VirtualBox graphical user interfaces. In particular,
          <computeroutput>VirtualBox</computeroutput>, the graphical
          VirtualBox manager, requires both Qt and SDL.
          <computeroutput>VBoxSDL</computeroutput>, the simplified GUI,
          requires only SDL. If you only want to run
          <computeroutput>VBoxHeadless</computeroutput>, neither Qt nor
          SDL are required.
        </para>
      </note>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="externalkernelmodules">

      <title>The VirtualBox Driver Modules</title>

      <para>
        In order to run other operating systems in virtual machines
        alongside your main operating system, VirtualBox needs to
        integrate very tightly into the system. To do this it installs a
        driver module called <computeroutput>vboxdrv</computeroutput>
        which does a lot of that work into the system kernel, which is
        the part of the operating system which controls your processor
        and physical hardware. Without this kernel module, you can still
        use the VirtualBox manager to configure virtual machines, but
        they will not start. It also installs network drivers called
        <computeroutput>vboxnetflt</computeroutput> and
        <computeroutput>vboxnetadp</computeroutput> which enable virtual
        machines to make more use of your computer's network
        capabilities and are needed for any virtual machine networking
        beyond the basic NAT mode.
      </para>

      <para>
        Since distributing driver modules separately from the kernel is
        not something which Linux supports well, the install process
        creates the modules on the system where they will be used. This
        usually means first installing software packages from the
        distribution which are needed for the build process. Normally,
        these will be the GNU compiler (GCC), GNU Make (make) and
        packages containing header files for your kernel, as well as
        making sure that all system updates are installed and that the
        system is running the most up-to-date kernel included in the
        distribution. <emphasis>The running kernel and the header files
        must be updated to matching versions</emphasis>. The following
        list includes some instructions for common distributions. For
        most of them you may want to start by finding the version name
        of your kernel, using the command <computeroutput>uname
        -r</computeroutput> in a terminal. The instructions assume that
        you have not changed too much from the original installation,
        particularly not installed a different kernel type. If you have,
        then you will need to determine yourself what to set up.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            With Debian and Ubuntu-based distributions, you must install
            the correct version of the
            <computeroutput>linux-headers</computeroutput>, usually
            whichever of
            <computeroutput>linux-headers-generic</computeroutput>,
            <computeroutput>linux-headers-amd64</computeroutput>,
            <computeroutput>linux-headers-i686</computeroutput> or
            <computeroutput>linux-headers-i686-pae</computeroutput> best
            matches the kernel version name. Also, the
            <computeroutput>linux-kbuild </computeroutput> package if it
            exists. Basic Ubuntu releases should have the correct
            packages installed by default.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            On Fedora, Redhat, Oracle Linux and many other RPM-based
            systems, the kernel version sometimes has a code of letters
            or a word close to the end of the version name. For example
            "uek" for the Oracle Enterprise kernel or "default" or
            "desktop" for the standard SUSE kernels. In this case, the
            package name is
            <computeroutput>kernel-uek-devel</computeroutput> or
            equivalent. If there is no such code, it is usually
            <computeroutput>kernel-devel</computeroutput>.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            On older SUSE and openSUSE Linux, you must install the
            <computeroutput>kernel-source</computeroutput> and
            <computeroutput>kernel-syms</computeroutput> packages.
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        If you suspect that something has gone wrong with module
        installation, check that your system is set up as described
        above and try running the following command, as root:
      </para>

<screen>rcvboxdrv setup</screen>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="install-linux-performing">

      <title>Performing the Installation</title>

      <para>
        VirtualBox is available in a number of package formats native to
        various common Linux distributions> See
        <xref linkend="hostossupport" />. In addition, there is an
        alternative generic installer (.run) which should work on most
        Linux distributions. The generic installer packages are built on
        EL5 systems and thus require reasonably old versions of glibc
        (version 2.5) and other system libraries.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="install-linux-debian-ubuntu">

        <title>Installing VirtualBox from a Debian/Ubuntu Package</title>

        <para>
          Download the appropriate package for your distribution. The
          following examples assume that you are installing to a 32-bit
          Ubuntu Wily system. Use <computeroutput>dpkg</computeroutput>
          to install the Debian package,as follows:
        </para>

<screen>sudo dpkg -i virtualbox-5.0_<replaceable>version-number</replaceable>_Ubuntu_wily_i386.deb</screen>

        <para>
          The installer will also try to build kernel modules suitable
          for the current running kernel. If the build process is not
          successful you will be shown a warning and the package will be
          left unconfigured. Look at
          <computeroutput>/var/log/vbox-install.log</computeroutput> to
          find out why the compilation failed. You may have to install
          the appropriate Linux kernel headers, see
          <xref
        linkend="externalkernelmodules" />. After
          correcting any problems, run the following command:
        </para>

<screen>sudo rcvboxdrv setup</screen>

        <para>
          This will start a second attempt to build the module.
        </para>

        <para>
          If a suitable kernel module was found in the package or the
          module was successfully built, the installation script will
          attempt to load that module. If this fails, please see
          <xref
        linkend="ts_linux-kernelmodule-fails-to-load" />
          for further information.
        </para>

        <para>
          Once VirtualBox has been successfully installed and
          configured, you can start it by clicking
          <emphasis role="bold">VirtualBox</emphasis> in your Start menu
          or from the command line. See
          <xref linkend="startingvboxonlinux" />.
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="install-linux-alt-installer">

        <title>Using the Alternative Generic Installer (VirtualBox.run)</title>

        <para>
          The alternative generic installer performs the following
          steps:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              Unpacks the application files to the target directory,

<screen>/opt/VirtualBox/</screen>

              which cannot be changed.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              Builds and installs the VirtualBox kernel modules:
              <computeroutput>vboxdrv</computeroutput>,
              <computeroutput>vboxnetflt</computeroutput>, and
              <computeroutput>vboxnetadp</computeroutput>.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              Creates <computeroutput>/sbin/rcvboxdrv</computeroutput>,
              an init script to start the VirtualBox kernel module.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              Creates a new system group called
              <computeroutput>vboxusers</computeroutput>.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              Creates symbolic links in
              <computeroutput>/usr/bin</computeroutput> to a shell
              script
              <computeroutput>/opt/VirtualBox/VBox</computeroutput>
              which does some sanity checks and dispatches to the actual
              executables: <computeroutput>VirtualBox</computeroutput>,
              <computeroutput>VBoxSDL</computeroutput>,
              <computeroutput>VBoxVRDP</computeroutput>,
              <computeroutput>VBoxHeadless</computeroutput> and
              <computeroutput>VBoxManage</computeroutput>
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              Creates
              <computeroutput>/etc/udev/rules.d/60-vboxdrv.rules</computeroutput>,
              a description file for udev, if that is present, which
              makes the USB devices accessible to all users in the
              <computeroutput>vboxusers</computeroutput> group.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              Writes the installation directory to
              <computeroutput>/etc/vbox/vbox.cfg</computeroutput>.
            </para>
          </listitem>

        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
          The installer must be executed as root with either
          <computeroutput>install</computeroutput> or
          <computeroutput>uninstall</computeroutput> as the first
          parameter. For example;
        </para>

<screen>sudo ./VirtualBox.run install</screen>

        <para>
          Or if you do not have the
          <computeroutput>sudo</computeroutput> command available, run
          the following as root instead:

<screen>./VirtualBox.run install</screen>
        </para>

        <para>
          Add every user who needs to access USB devices from a
          VirtualBox guests to the group
          <computeroutput>vboxusers</computeroutput>. Either use the GUI
          user management tools or run the following command as root:
        </para>

<screen>sudo usermod -a -G vboxusers username</screen>

        <note>
          <para>
            The <computeroutput>usermod</computeroutput> command of some
            older Linux distributions does not support the
            <computeroutput>-a</computeroutput> option, which adds the
            user to the given group without affecting membership of
            other groups. In this case, find out the current group
            memberships with the <computeroutput>groups</computeroutput>
            command and add all these groups in a comma-separated list
            to the command line after the
            <computeroutput>-G</computeroutput> option. For example:
            <computeroutput>usermod -G group1,group2,vboxusers
            username</computeroutput>.
          </para>
        </note>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="install-linux-manual">

        <title>Performing a Manual Installation</title>

        <para>
          If you cannot use the shell script installer described in
          <xref linkend="install-linux-alt-installer"/>, you can perform
          a manual installation. Invoke the installer as follows:
        </para>

<screen>./VirtualBox.run --keep --noexec</screen>

        <para>
          This will unpack all the files needed for installation in the
          directory <computeroutput>install</computeroutput> under the
          current directory. The VirtualBox application files are
          contained in
          <computeroutput>VirtualBox.tar.bz2</computeroutput> which you
          can unpack to any directory on your system. For example:
        </para>

<screen>sudo mkdir /opt/VirtualBox
sudo tar jxf ./install/VirtualBox.tar.bz2 -C /opt/VirtualBox</screen>

        <para>
          or as root:

<screen>mkdir /opt/VirtualBox
tar jxf ./install/VirtualBox.tar.bz2 -C /opt/VirtualBox</screen>
        </para>

        <para>
          The sources for VirtualBox's kernel module are provided in the
          <computeroutput>src</computeroutput> directory. To build the
          module, change to the directory and issue
        </para>

<screen>make</screen>

        <para>
          If everything builds correctly, issue the following command to
          install the module to the appropriate module directory:
        </para>

<screen>sudo make install</screen>

        <para>
          In case you do not have sudo, switch the user account to root
          and run the following command:

<screen>make install</screen>
        </para>

        <para>
          The VirtualBox kernel module needs a device node to operate.
          The above make command will tell you how to create the device
          node, depending on your Linux system. The procedure is
          slightly different for a classical Linux setup with a
          <computeroutput>/dev</computeroutput> directory, a system with
          the now deprecated <computeroutput>devfs</computeroutput> and
          a modern Linux system with
          <computeroutput>udev</computeroutput>.
        </para>

        <para>
          On certain Linux distributions, you might experience
          difficulties building the module. You will have to analyze the
          error messages from the build system to diagnose the cause of
          the problems. In general, make sure that the correct Linux
          kernel sources are used for the build process.
        </para>

        <para>
          Note that the <computeroutput>/dev/vboxdrv</computeroutput>
          kernel module device node must be owned by root:root and must
          be read/writable only for the user.
        </para>

        <para>
          Next, you install the system initialization script for the
          kernel module and activate the initialization script using the
          right method for your distribution, as follows:

<screen>cp /opt/VirtualBox/vboxdrv.sh /sbin/rcvboxdrv</screen>

          This example assumes you installed VirtualBox to the
          <computeroutput>/opt/VirtualBox</computeroutput> directory.
          Create a configuration file for VitrualBox:

<screen>mkdir /etc/vbox
echo INSTALL_DIR=/opt/VirtualBox &gt; /etc/vbox/vbox.cfg</screen>

          Create the following symbolic links:
        </para>

<screen>ln -sf /opt/VirtualBox/VBox.sh /usr/bin/VirtualBox
ln -sf /opt/VirtualBox/VBox.sh /usr/bin/VBoxManage
ln -sf /opt/VirtualBox/VBox.sh /usr/bin/VBoxHeadless
ln -sf /opt/VirtualBox/VBox.sh /usr/bin/VBoxSDL</screen>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="install-linux-update-uninstall">

        <title>Updating and Uninstalling VirtualBox</title>

        <para>
          Before updating or uninstalling VirtualBox, you must terminate
          any virtual machines which are currently running and exit the
          VirtualBox or VBoxSVC applications. To update VirtualBox,
          simply run the installer of the updated version. To uninstall
          VirtualBox, invoke the installer like this:

<screen>sudo ./VirtualBox.run uninstall</screen>

          or as root:

<screen>./VirtualBox.run uninstall</screen>

          Starting with version 2.2.2, you can uninstall the .run
          package as follows:

<screen>/opt/VirtualBox/uninstall.sh</screen>

          To manually uninstall VirtualBox, simply perform the manual
          installation steps in reverse order.
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="install-linux-debian-automatic">

        <title>Automatic Installation of Debian Packages</title>

        <para>
          The Debian packages will request some user feedback when
          installed for the first time. The debconf system is used to
          perform this task. To prevent any user interaction during
          installation, default values can be defined. A file
          <computeroutput>vboxconf</computeroutput> can contain the
          following debconf settings:

<screen>virtualbox virtualbox/module-compilation-allowed boolean true
virtualbox virtualbox/delete-old-modules boolean true</screen>

          The first line allows compilation of the vboxdrv kernel module
          if no module was found for the current kernel. The second line
          allows the package to delete any old vboxdrv kernel modules
          compiled by previous installations.
        </para>

        <para>
          These default settings can be applied prior to the
          installation of the VirtualBox Debian package, as follows:
        </para>

<screen>debconf-set-selections vboxconf</screen>

        <para>
          In addition there are some common configuration options that
          can be set prior to the installation. See
          <xref
        linkend="linux_install_opts" />.
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="install-linux-rpm-automatic">

        <title>Automatic Installation of RPM Packages</title>

        <para>
          The RPM format does not provide a configuration system
          comparable to the debconf system. See
          <xref
        linkend="linux_install_opts" /> for how to set
          some common installation options provided by VirtualBox.
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="linux_install_opts">

        <title>Automatic Installation Options</title>

        <para>
          To configure the installation process for .deb and .rpm
          packages, you can create a response file named
          <computeroutput>/etc/default/virtualbox</computeroutput>. The
          automatic generation of the udev rule can be prevented by the
          following setting:

<screen>INSTALL_NO_UDEV=1</screen>

          The creation of the group vboxusers can be prevented as
          follows:

<screen>INSTALL_NO_GROUP=1</screen>

          If the following line is specified, the package installer will
          not try to build the <computeroutput>vboxdrv</computeroutput>
          kernel module if no module fitting the current kernel was
          found.
        </para>

<screen>INSTALL_NO_VBOXDRV=1</screen>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="install-linux-vboxusers">

      <title>The vboxusers Group</title>

      <para>
        The Linux installers create the system user group
        <computeroutput>vboxusers</computeroutput> during installation.
        Any system user who is going to use USB devices from VirtualBox
        guests must be a member of that group. A user can be made a
        member of the group <computeroutput>vboxusers</computeroutput>
        through the GUI user/group management or using the following
        command:
      </para>

<screen>sudo usermod -a -G vboxusers username</screen>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="startingvboxonlinux">

      <title>Starting VirtualBox on Linux</title>

      <para>
        The easiest way to start a VirtualBox program is by running the
        program of your choice
        (<computeroutput>VirtualBox</computeroutput>,
        <computeroutput>VBoxManage</computeroutput>,
        <computeroutput>VBoxSDL</computeroutput>, or
        <computeroutput>VBoxHeadless</computeroutput>) from a terminal.
        These are symbolic links to
        <computeroutput>VBox.sh</computeroutput> that start the required
        program for you.
      </para>

      <para>
        The following detailed instructions should only be of interest
        if you wish to execute VirtualBox without installing it first.
        You should start by compiling the
        <computeroutput>vboxdrv</computeroutput> kernel module and
        inserting it into the Linux kernel. VirtualBox consists of a
        service daemon, <computeroutput>VBoxSVC</computeroutput>, and
        several application programs. The daemon is automatically
        started if necessary. All VirtualBox applications will
        communicate with the daemon through Unix local domain sockets.
        There can be multiple daemon instances under different user
        accounts and applications can only communicate with the daemon
        running under the user account as the application. The local
        domain socket resides in a subdirectory of your system's
        directory for temporary files called
        <computeroutput>.vbox-&lt;username&gt;-ipc</computeroutput>. In
        case of communication problems or server startup problems, you
        may try to remove this directory.
      </para>

      <para>
        All VirtualBox applications
        (<computeroutput>VirtualBox</computeroutput>,
        <computeroutput>VBoxSDL</computeroutput>,
        <computeroutput>VBoxManage</computeroutput>, and
        <computeroutput>VBoxHeadless</computeroutput>) require the
        VirtualBox directory to be in the library path, as follows:
      </para>

<screen>LD_LIBRARY_PATH=. ./VBoxManage showvminfo "Windows XP"</screen>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="install-solaris-host">

    <title>Installing on Solaris Hosts</title>

    <para>
      For the specific versions of Solaris that are supported as host
      operating systems, see <xref
    linkend="hostossupport" />.
    </para>

    <para>
      If you have a previously installed instance of VirtualBox on your
      Solaris host, please uninstall it first before installing a new
      instance. See <xref linkend="uninstall-solaris-host" /> for
      uninstall instructions.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="install-solaris-performing">

      <title>Performing the Installation</title>

      <para>
        VirtualBox is available as a standard Solaris package. Download
        the VirtualBox SunOS package which includes the 64-bit versions
        of VirtualBox. <emphasis>The installation must be performed as
        root and from the global zone</emphasis> as the VirtualBox
        installer loads kernel drivers which cannot be done from
        non-global zones. To verify which zone you are currently in,
        execute the <computeroutput>zonename</computeroutput> command.
        Execute the following commands:
      </para>

<screen>gunzip -cd VirtualBox-<replaceable>version-number</replaceable>-SunOS.tar.gz | tar xvf -</screen>

      <para>
        Starting with VirtualBox 3.1 the VirtualBox kernel package is no
        longer a separate package and has been integrated into the main
        package. Install the VirtualBox package as follows:
      </para>

<screen>pkgadd -d VirtualBox-<replaceable>version-number</replaceable>-SunOS.pkg</screen>

      <para>
        The installer will then prompt you to enter the package you wish
        to install. Choose <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis> or
        <emphasis role="bold">all</emphasis> and proceed. Next the
        installer will ask you if you want to allow the postinstall
        script to be executed. Choose <emphasis role="bold">y</emphasis>
        and proceed, as it is essential to execute this script which
        installs the VirtualBox kernel module. Following this
        confirmation the installer will install VirtualBox and execute
        the postinstall setup script.
      </para>

      <para>
        Once the postinstall script has been executed your installation
        is now complete. You may now safely delete the uncompressed
        package and <computeroutput>autoresponse</computeroutput> files
        from your system. VirtualBox is installed in
        <computeroutput>/opt/VirtualBox</computeroutput>.
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>
          If you need to use VirtualBox from non-global zones, see
          <xref linkend="solaris-zones" />.
        </para>
      </note>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="install-solaris-vboxuser">

      <title>The vboxuser Group</title>

      <para>
        Starting with VirtualBox 4.1, the installer creates the system
        user group <computeroutput>vboxuser</computeroutput> during
        installation for Solaris hosts that support the USB features
        required by VirtualBox. Any system user who is going to use USB
        devices from VirtualBox guests must be a member of this group. A
        user can be made a member of this group through the GUI
        user/group management or at the command line by executing as
        root:
      </para>

<screen>usermod -G vboxuser username</screen>

      <para>
        Note that adding an active user to that group will require that
        user to log out and back in again. This should be done manually
        after successful installation of the package.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="install-solaris-starting">

      <title>Starting VirtualBox on Solaris</title>

      <para>
        The easiest way to start a VirtualBox program is by running the
        program of your choice
        (<computeroutput>VirtualBox</computeroutput>,
        <computeroutput>VBoxManage</computeroutput>,
        <computeroutput>VBoxSDL</computeroutput>, or
        <computeroutput>VBoxHeadless</computeroutput>) from a terminal.
        These are symbolic links to
        <computeroutput>VBox.sh</computeroutput> that start the required
        program for you.
      </para>

      <para>
        Alternatively, you can directly invoke the required programs
        from <computeroutput>/opt/VirtualBox</computeroutput>. Using the
        links provided is easier as you do not have to type the full
        path.
      </para>

      <para>
        You can configure some elements of the
        <computeroutput>VirtualBox</computeroutput> Qt GUI, such as
        fonts and colours, by running
        <computeroutput>VBoxQtconfig</computeroutput> from the terminal.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="uninstall-solaris-host">

      <title>Uninstallation</title>

      <para>
        Uninstallation of VirtualBox on Solaris requires root
        permissions. To perform the uninstallation, start a root
        terminal session and run the following command:
      </para>

<screen>pkgrm SUNWvbox</screen>

      <para>
        After confirmation, this will remove VirtualBox from your
        system.
      </para>

      <para>
        If you are uninstalling VirtualBox version 3.0 or lower, you
        need to remove the VirtualBox kernel interface package, as
        follows:
      </para>

      <para>
<screen>pkgrm SUNWvboxkern</screen>
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="install-solaris-unattended">

      <title>Unattended Installation</title>

      <para>
        To perform a non-interactive installation of VirtualBox there is
        a response file named
        <computeroutput>autoresponse</computeroutput>, that the
        installer will use for responses to inputs rather than ask them
        from you.
      </para>

      <para>
        Extract the tar.gz package as described in the normal
        installation instructions. Then open a root terminal session and
        run the following command:
      </para>

<screen>pkgadd -d VirtualBox-<replaceable>version-number</replaceable>-SunOS-x86 -n -a autoresponse SUNWvbox</screen>

      <para>
        To perform a non-interactive uninstallation, open a root
        terminal session and run the following command:
      </para>

<screen>pkgrm -n -a /opt/VirtualBox/autoresponse SUNWvbox</screen>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="solaris-zones">

      <title>Configuring a Zone for Running VirtualBox</title>

      <para>
        Assuming that VirtualBox has already been installed into your
        zone, you need to give the zone access to VirtualBox's device
        node. This is done by performing the following steps. Start a
        root terminal and run the following command:
      </para>

<screen>zonecfg -z vboxzone</screen>

      <para>
        Replace "vboxzone" with the name of the zone where you intend to
        run VirtualBox.
      </para>

      <para>
        Use<computeroutput>zonecfg</computeroutput> to add the
        <computeroutput>device</computeroutput> resource and
        <computeroutput>match</computeroutput> properties to the zone,
        as follows:
      </para>

<screen>zonecfg:vboxzone&gt;add device
zonecfg:vboxzone:device&gt;set match=/dev/vboxdrv
zonecfg:vboxzone:device&gt;end
zonecfg:vboxzone&gt;add device
zonecfg:vboxzone:device&gt;set match=/dev/vboxdrvu
zonecfg:vboxzone:device&gt;end
zonecfg:vboxzone&gt;exit</screen>

      <para>
        If you are running VirtualBox 2.2.0 or above on Solaris 11 or
        above, you may also add a device for
        <computeroutput>/dev/vboxusbmon</computeroutput>, similar to
        that shown above. This does not apply to Solaris 10 hosts, due
        to lack of USB support.
      </para>

      <para>
        If you are not using sparse root zones, you will need to
        loopback mount <computeroutput>/opt/VirtualBox</computeroutput>
        from the global zone into the non-global zone at the same path.
        This is specified below using the
        <computeroutput>dir</computeroutput> attribute and the
        <computeroutput>special</computeroutput> attribute. For example:
      </para>

<screen>zonecfg:vboxzone&gt;add fs
zonecfg:vboxzone:device&gt;set dir=/opt/VirtualBox
zonecfg:vboxzone:device&gt;set special=/opt/VirtualBox
zonecfg:vboxzone:device&gt;set type=lofs
zonecfg:vboxzone:device&gt;end
zonecfg:vboxzone&gt;exit</screen>

      <para>
        Reboot the zone using <computeroutput>zoneadm</computeroutput>
        and you should be able to run VirtualBox from within the
        configured zone.
      </para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

</chapter>
