<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
 
<chapter> <!-- HACK ALERT! Seems we must have a single top level element for xi:include to work.
                           So, we use chapter and xpointer="xpointer(/chapter/)" with xi:include. -->
  <sect1>
    <title>Version 5.0.0 (2015-07-09)</title>

    <para>This is a major update. The following major new features
      were added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>Paravirtualization support for Windows and Linux guests to improve
          time-keeping accuracy and performance (see  <xref linkend="gimproviders" />)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Make more instruction set extensions available to the guest when
          running with hardware-assisted virtualization and nested paging. Among
          others this includes: SSE 4.1, SSE4.2, AVX, AVX-2, AES-NI,
          <emphasis>POPCNT</emphasis>, <emphasis>RDRAND</emphasis> and
          <emphasis>RDSEED</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>xHCI Controller to support USB 3 devices
          (see <xref linkend="settings-usb" />)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Drag and drop support (bidirectional) for Windows, Linux and Solaris guests</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Disk image encryption (see <xref linkend="diskencryption" />)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMs can now be started in <emphasis>separate mode</emphasis>. The VM
          process is started headless while the frontend runs as a separate process
          which can be terminated without stopping the VM.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: VM guest-content scaling support (including 3D acceleration)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: New User Interface settings page for customizing status-bar,
          menu-bar and guest-content scaling</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: New Encryption settings tab for customizing encryption options for
          disk images</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: HiDPI support including application icons and optional unscaled HiDPI
          output on Mac OS X (including 3D acceleration)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: Hotplugging support for SATA disks</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>New, modular audio architecture for providing a better abstraction of the host
          audio backends</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Support for the NDIS6 networking framework on Windows (default on Vista
          and later)</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para>In addition, the following items were fixed and/or added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: improved timing on Solaris hosts with older VT-x hosts
          without preemption timers</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: further improvements for TSC frequency measurements and
          guest timekeeping</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: debug facility now includes the guest CPU's
          FPU/SSE/extended state in the core dump</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed a hang under rare conditions on 32-bit hosts</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: several fixes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: improved HID LEDs synchronization for Mac and Windows hosts.
          The physical LEDs state now restored together with the VM state.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: take the guest screen aspect ratio into account for the
          preview window</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: provide direct access to storage media in the VM selector</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: allow to save the VM state from the selector even if the VM
          is already paused</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxManage: when exporting an appliance, support the suppression
          of MAC addresses, which means they will be always recreated on
          import, avoiding duplicate MAC addresses for VMs which are imported
          several times</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxManage: now supports renaming storage controllers and USB controllers</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Guest Control: major overhaul, for example fixing wrong parameter quoting
          (bug #13157)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>USB: added USB traffic capturing (see <xref linkend="usbtrafficcapturing" />)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Made resizing X11 guests work more reliably</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: block the removal of the current snapshot if it has child
          snapshots (only relevant for VMs without snapshottable hard disks,
          their presence always prevented removal), which resulted in VM
          config corruption</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: mark VM configs with snapshots but without current snapshot
          as inaccessible, as this combination is nonsense</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: fix information for some automatically generated events
           (only with XPCOM, Windows host was not affected), which caused
           errors when getting some of the attributes over the webservice
           (bug #12379)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: fix crashes in Java API clients using the XPCOM binding,
          happened with output parameters only (bug #11232)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: a number of settings (e.g. network settings) can now also
          be changed when the VM is in saved state</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: fixed incorrect resuming of VMs on host-resume unless they were
          previously paused due to a host-suspend</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: don't lose the saved state and "current state changed" flag
          during cloning of a VM</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: OS type description consistency fix (bug #14162)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxSVC: don't keep the support driver permanently open</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Main/Properties: properly drop transient guest properties when
          the VM is powered off</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VRDP: fixed a couple of races which may cause a crash during
          VM poweroff</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ExtPack: don't fail if the TMP directory contains non-latin1
          characters (bug #14159)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D: fix potential race in which might cause a crash on VM
          termination</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D: fixed a possible memory leak in the host service</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Serial: new TCP/IP backend (see <xref linkend="serialports"/>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: added USB mass storage device class
          (see <xref linkend="harddiskcontrollers"/>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: added <emphasis>vbox-img</emphasis> standalone tool for
          direct manipulation of virtual hard disk images without VBoxManage</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed crash as a result of I/O errors in certain conditions
          (bug #13105)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: fixed several potential crashes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: don't forcibly reset/drop all connections when the link goes
          down</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Netsniffer: properly handle changing of the trace file name
          at VM runtime</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Audio: fixed audio output and input when changing the default audio device
          more than once on OS X</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Audio: fixed audio input on OS X under certain circumstances</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ICH9: fixed the interrupt disable logic for MSI interrupts; should
          fix old Linux guests with AHCI</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>USB: improve playback with USB sound devices attached to the emulated
          OHCI controller</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Audio: provide Linux guests a different AC97 audio codec type so Linux
          ALSA does not mis-detect the link speed (default for new VMs)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>BIOS: fix for booting from SCSI CD/DVD media</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>BIOS: fix for reads partially beyond end of disk (bug #14021)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VRDP: fixed listening for IPv6 on some systems (bug #14038)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>rdesktop-vrdp: upgraded to version 1.8.3</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux hosts: fixed a bug which made the netfilter driver ignore
          certain events (bug #12264)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X hosts: El Capitan fixes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X hosts: fixed a bug which might trigger a host kernel panic
          if a VM is started and another hypervisor is active</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Solaris hosts: Solaris 12 installer fix</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Guest Additions: added a heartbeat service
          (see <xref linkend="heartbeatservice" />)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux hosts / guests: support for Linux distributions using systemd
          without sysv emulation (e.g. ArchLinux)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions/WDDM: improved video memory utilization and
          allow more/bigger guest screens with large resolutions (including HiDPI)
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux Additions: added <emphasis>-s</emphasis> parameter to
          <emphasis>mount.vboxsf</emphasis> to be sloppy with invalid parameters</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>X11 Additions: fixed wrong DPI value (bug #14151)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X guests: limit the CPU family for legacy guests</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Solaris Additions: added quiesce support to co-operate with Solaris'
          fast-reboot feature</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Version 4.3.28 (2015-05-13)</title>

    <para>This is a maintenance release. The following items were fixed and/or
      added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed a Guru Meditation when rebooting certain guests (for
          example Solaris doing fast reboot) by fixing the implementation for INIT IPI</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: added some information for diagnosing rare
          <emphasis>VERR_VMX_INVALID_VMXON_PTR</emphasis> Guru Meditations (VT-x only)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: HID LEDs sync: prevent synchronization if VM window has no focus
          (Windows and Mac OS X hosts only)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed drag and drop moving the cursor between guest screens on
          certain hosts</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D: fixed a crash on restoring the VM state on X11 hosts (bug #12737)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D: fixed a crash on restoring the VM state</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D: fixed a crash on Linux guest shutdown (bug #12772)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VRDP: fixed incompatibility with rdesktop 1.8.3</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VRDP: fixed listening for IPv6 on some systems (bug #14038)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: don't crash if creating an asynchronous I/O context
          fails (e.g. when starting many VMs) and show a proper error message</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Floppy: several fixes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Audio: improved the behavior of the volume control for the
          HD audio device emulation</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>USB: increase the number of supported drivers from 3 to 5
          (Windows hosts only)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>PS/2 keyboard: synchronize the LED state on VM restore
          (Windows and Mac OS X hosts only)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT Network: when running multiple NAT networks with multiple VMs,
          only stop the respective services when stopping VMs (bug #14090)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: don't kill UDP bindings on ICMP errors (bug #13475)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: bandwidth limit now works properly with NAT (bug #11485)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>BIOS: fixed the returned size value of the VBE 2.0 PMI function 0Ah
          (4.2.0 regression; bug #14096)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Guest Control: fixed parameter quoting in Windows guests
          (bug #13157)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Webcam passthrough improvements for Linux (V4L2) hosts to support more
          webcam models</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: don't fail starting a VM with <emphasis>VBOX_E_INVALID_OBJECT_STATE</emphasis>
          under certain conditions (bug #13617)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: be more verbose on <emphasis>VBOX_E_INVALID_OBJECT_STATE</emphasis>
          if a medium is attached to a running VM (bug #13560)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: fixed a bug which could result in losing certain screen resize
          events with multi-monitor guests</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>rdesktop-vrdp: fixed path to the keymaps (bug #12066)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>rdesktop-vrdp: switch to version 1.8.3</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows hosts: more hardening fixes (e.g. bugs #14051, #14052)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux hosts: another fix for activated SMAP on Linux 3.19
          and newer (Broadwell and later; bug #13961)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux hosts: Linux 4.1 compile fix (bug #14081)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Solaris hosts: fixed using of VNIC templates with Crossbow based
          bridged networking to be compatible with vanity interface names</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X hosts: fixed crash during VM termination under rare
          circumstances</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions/WDDM: improved video memory utilization and allow
          more/bigger guest screens with large resolutions (including HiDPI)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>X11 Additions: prevent flickering when updating mouse cursor</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Solaris Additions: fixed incorrect usage of 'prtconf' while
          installing Guest Additions (Solaris 10 only)</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Version 4.3.26 (2015-03-16)</title>

    <para>This is a maintenance release. The following items were fixed and/or
      added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: in the snapshots pane, protect the age of snapshots against
          wrong host time (bug #13955)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT Network: fixed a bug which prevented to propagate any DNS
          name server / domain / search string information to the NAT network
          (4.3.24 regression; bugs #13915, #13918)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT Network: don't delay the shutdown of VBoxSVC on
          Windows hosts</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mouse support: the mouse could not be moved under rare
          conditions if no Guest Additions are installed (4.3.24 regression;
          bug #13935)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: if the guest ejects a virtual CD/DVD medium, make the
          change permanent (bugs #9858, #12885)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VGA: made saving secondary screen sizes possible in X11 guests</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>SDK: fixed the VirtualBox.tlb file (4.3.20 regression; bug #13943)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>rdesktop-vrdp: make it work with USB devices again
          (4.3.14 regression; bug #13901)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>USB: fixed a possible BSOD on Windows hosts under rare conditions</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>iPXE: enable the HTTP download protocol on non-Linux hosts (bug #13628)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X hosts: don't panic on hosts with activated SMAP (Broadwell
          and later; bug #13951)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux hosts: don't crash Linux 4.0 hosts (bug #13835)</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Version 4.3.24 (2015-03-02)</title>

    <para>This is a maintenance release. The following items were fixed and/or
      added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: emulation fix for the <emphasis>ENTER</emphasis> instruction
          under certain conditions; fixes Solaris 10 guests (VT-x without
          unrestricted guest execution)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fix for handling NMIs on Linux hosts with X2APIC enabled</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT/NAT Network: fix connection drops when the host's DHCP lease
          was renewed (4.3.22 regression; Windows hosts only; bug #13839)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: don't crash on an empty domain list when switching the
          DNS host configuration (4.3.22 regression; Mac OS X hosts only;
          bug #13874)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>PXE: re-enable it on Windows hosts (4.3.22 regression; Windows hosts
          only; bug #13842)
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Shared Folders: fixed a problem with Windows guests (4.3.22 regression;
          bug #13786)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Audio: improved record quality when using the DirectSound audio
          backend</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxManage: when executing the <emphasis>controlvm</emphasis> command
          take care that the corresponding VM runtime changes are saved permanently
          (bug #13892)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Installer: properly install the 32-bit version of VBoxRes.dll
          on 32-bit hosts (bug #13876)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux hosts / guests: Linux 4.0 fixes (bug #13835)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>OS/2 Additions: fixed mouse integration (4.3.22 regression;
          bug #13825)</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Version 4.3.22 (2015-02-12)</title>

    <para>This is a maintenance release. The following items were fixed and/or
      added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: refined measurement of TSC frequency on the host, improves
          timekeeping for guests</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: decreased CPU load resulting from guest MMIO writes to the
          virtual APIC</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed interception of debug exceptions, observed while using
          the dbx debugger on Solaris guests (VT-x only)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: 3D overlay window positioning code improved, fixed potential
          misplacement of 3D accelerated guest graphics content</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed accident SSL authentication failures during update
          check on Windows hosts (bug #12969)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: never send the "ACPI power" keyboard scancode to the guest,
          we have the ACPI power button for that</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: was unable to properly restore seamless mode VM from
          snapshot/saved-state under some circumstances</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxHeadless: don't crash if 3D is enabled in the VM settings
          (bug #10250)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ATA: fixed several passthrough issues (bugs #12310, #1360)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Audio: fixed DirectSound failure when the the host has no audio
          input device (Windows hosts only; bug #9205)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>SB16: fixed compatibility issue (bug #13769)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed broken CD/DVD passthrough when using the
          IDE controller (bug #12310)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: new ping proxy for Windows hosts (bug #11871)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: Properly report outbound connect(2) failures to
          guest with TCP RST or ICMP (bug #10525)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT Network: no need for frequent wakeups in VBoxNetDHCP
          and VBoxNetNAT (bug #11681)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Host-only adapter: prevent Windows from creating an "Unidentified
          network" (bug #9688)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Bridged Networking: don't leak host-to-guest traffic to
          the wireless network when bridging to a wireless interface
          (bug #13714)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Main: fixed a possible race when changing the medium leading
          to a deadlock under rare conditions (bug #13722)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxManage: fixed return code if starting a VM failed
          (bug #13773)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Settings: on Windows host, do not use environment variable HOME
          at all, the settings location is derived from the user profile
          directory (bug #7689)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: fixed 2 deadlock opportunities related to medium handling
          (bugs #13789, #13801, thank you Alexander Urakov)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: fixed bug in XPCOM which created too few worker threads,
          sporadically resulting in a deadlock (bug #13802, thank you Alexander
          Urakov)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>SDK: fixed a garbage collection leak in the Python VirtualBox
          webservice API binding (bug #13817)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux hosts: fixes for activated SMAP (Broadwell and later,
          bug #13820)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>X11 guests: prevent unwanted hiding of guest screens
          on multi-monitor guests (bug #13287)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>X11 guests: added support for X.Org Server 1.17</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>X11 Additions: fixed a memory leak in VBoxService if libdbus
          is available but dbus-daemon isn't running (bug #13770)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions: prevent VBox WDDM driver from loading if host
          reports weak OpenGL capabilities. 3D content now can be shown over
          Remote Desktop connection.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Winodws Additions: some fixes for recent Windows 10 Previews</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux Additions: fixed a compatibility issue with 64-bit
          Linux 2.4 kernels</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux Additions: fixed a potential use-after-free when unloading
          the VBoxGuest module</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux Additions: Linux 3.19 fixes (bug #13741)</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Version 4.3.20 (2014-11-21)</title>

    <para>This is a maintenance release. The following items were fixed and/or
      added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed reboot hang of 32-bit Windows SMP guests (bugs #13319,
          #13462)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: proper <emphasis>Math Fault</emphasis> handling with certain
          legacy guests (bug #9042, AMD hosts)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed a Guru Meditation <emphasis>VINF_EM_TRIPLE_FAULT</emphasis>
          on older CPUs that don't support MSR-bitmaps (VT-x only;
          bugs #13034, #13125, #13311, #13425, #13426, #13463, #13585)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fix 3D overlay window reparenting issue when VM goes to
          fullscreen mode on X11 hosts</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fix occasional loss of focus in full-screen mode on X11
           host systems (4.3.16 regression)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: Mac OS X: wizards should have Cancel button
          (bug #12541)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: added a global option to prevent automatic raising of the
          new window by mouse move with multi-screen guests (bug #8878)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: accept remote display port 0 as the default RDP port
          (bug #8534)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxManage: fixed crash when executing <emphasis>showvminfo</emphasis>
          command under certain circumstances (bug #13190)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ACPI: fixed occassional Guru Meditations in ACPI timer code
          (4.3.18 regression; bug #13521)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>EFI: improved performance of IDE disk access</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>EFI: fixed a bug in the EFI video driver which prevented
          Windows to boot in UEFI mode (bug #12022)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>EFI: properly announce the amount of RAM for big VMs
          (bugs #11103 and #13211)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed a crash under certain cicrumstances when a medium
          was ejected from a drive attached to the SATA controller without
          inserting a new medium before pausing or closing the VM
          (4.3.16 regression) </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed an interrupt acknowledge issue causing hanging guests
          or slower I/O (4.3.18 regression)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed broken resume after the VM was suspended due to
          a full disk if host I/O caching is used</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed a Guru Meditation under certain conditions when
          using the DevLsiLogic controller with VMs running in raw mode
          (4.3 regression; bugs #12254, #12655, #12709, #12774, #12886)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Guest Control: fixed a bug which might lead to a crash during
          recursive copy</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>SDK: Java COM bindings fixes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>iPXE: enable the HTTP download protocol (bug #13628)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Runtime: do not use a fixed stack size creating temporary threads
           during initialization (bug #13038)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows hosts: fixed more startup problems on certain Windows hosts due
          to conflicts with anti-virus software; better error reporting
          (4.3.14 regression; bug #13187)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows hosts: fixed DirectSound host audio failure under certain conditions
          (bug #13418)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows hosts: fixed additional cases of 4.3.14 regression
          whereby AltGr stopped working for some people (bug #13216)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions: preserve guest monitor layout when resizing
          Windows 7 or newer guests</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux Additions: Linux 3.18 compile fixes (bug #13515)</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Version 4.3.18 (2014-10-10)</title>

    <para>This is a maintenance release. The following items were fixed and/or
      added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed a potential misbehavior after restoring the A20 state
          from a saved state</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed full-screen mode mini-toolbar related regressions
          for different platforms and window managers (bug #13369)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: X11: fixed full-screen mode Unity panels quirk caused by
          mini-toolbar code changes in last release (bug #13365)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: X11: added possibility to use legacy full-screen mode
          as the new one can cause multi-screen issues under Unity, see
          <xref linkend="legacy-fullscreen-mode" xreflabel="here"/> (bug #13365)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: Mac OS X: fixed full-screen mode artifact causing black screen
           when 3D acceleration was enabled on 10.10 Yosemite hosts (bug #13448)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: Mac OS X: fixed regression in user-space swiping from/to
          VBox in full-screen mode</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: Mac OS X: fixed issue with switching to VBox in full-screen
          mode through Alt+Tab and Mission Control</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed data corruption when resizing huge VHD images under
          certain circumstances (bug #11960)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed a rare hang during startup when the BIOS enumerates the
          storage devices attached to the SATA controller</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: follow the spec with AHCI interrupt acknowledge (bug #13474)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed broken iSCSI authentication (4.3.14 regression; bugs #13386,
          #13435)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT Network: properly parse port forwarding rules to allow UDP
          rules</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>USB: fixed a crash on Linux hosts with older Linux kernels (bug #13400) and
          several other fixes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ACPI: fixed ACPI timer anomalies (bug #12076)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Guest Control: fixed a memory leak (bug #13434)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Main: when removing a VM, do also remove the VBoxStartup.log file
          which might exist on Windows hosts (bug #13478)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows hosts: fixed more startup problems on certain Windows hosts due
          to conflicts with anti-virus software; better error reporting
          (4.3.14 regression; bug #13187)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows hosts: propagate the process startup information to the child
          process (4.3.14 regression; bug #13243)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X hosts: don't force using the discrete GPU (bug #11111)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions: some Windows 10 tweaks</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>X11 guests: fix a bug handling video driver display properties
           which prevented GNOME Shell on Fedora 21 from starting</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux hosts / guests: fixed a few remaining warnings in the kernel
          log if memory allocation fails (bug #11171)</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Version 4.3.16 (2014-09-09)</title>

    <para>This is a maintenance release. The following items were fixed and/or
      added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed restoring 32-bit FPU state on 64-bit capable VMs
          and restoring guest FPU in raw-mode VMs (bug #12646; 4.3 regression)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: properly restore normal/scale mode guest-screen size
          after exiting full-screen/seamless mode</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: mini-toolbar should provoke less artifacts/conflicts with
          3D guest rendering</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: Mac OS X: Native full-screen multi-screen transition
          was able to blackout host-screens for nearly minute</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: X11: Modern window managers should now use native full-screen
          multi-screen mapping API</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: added extradata item for configuring the mouse capture
          behavior, see <xref linkend="mouse-capture" xreflabel="here"/>
          (bug #3506)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed a VBoxSVC crash when querying an iSCSI target with
          authentication configured (4.3.14 regression)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed a rare data corruption during reads if another
          allocating write is running concurrently and accesses the same range</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed a rare crash for certain VHD images from other products</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed a rare release assertion when using the AHCI controller</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Floppy: fixed read errors and guest memory corruption when running
          under control of QEMM</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D: added experimental support for rendering on offline GPUs for Mac OS X host</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D: fixed white window appearing on entering FullScreen mode on Mac OS X host</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D: fixed video recording support for 3D data regression (bug #13073)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D: fixes for MS Office 2013 support</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D: several fixes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Bridged Networking: improved IPv6 support when bridging
          to a wireless interface</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: prevent internal DNS service from stuck in host-resolver mode
          when host was switched from one network to another one while host was
          sleeping (Mac OS X hosts)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: preserve DF (if possible) and TOS when proxying
          outbound UDP datagrams (bugs #9440, #12309)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: don't let multicast datagrams out (bug #7338)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: fixed handling of large incoming UDP datagrams on
          Windows hosts (bug #12136)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: fixed handling of the RFC 1533 DHCP PAD option</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT Network: fixed inbound half-close on Windows hosts</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT Network: preserve IPv4 DF (if possible), TTL, TOS
          and IPv6 Hop Limit when proxying outbound UDP
          datagrams</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VRDP: fixed a rare crash when using remote audio input</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>USB: fixed several regressions from 4.3.14 (bug #13320)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Audio: made the HDA sound emulation work with certain Mac OS X guests
          (e.g. Mountain Lion)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows hosts: fixed startup problems on certain Windows hosts due
          to conflicts with anti-virus software (4.3.14 regression; bug #13187)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows hosts: fixed 4.3.14 regression whereby AltGr stopped
          working for some people (bug #13216)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>X11 hosts: made the extra key on Brazilian Thinkpads work
          (bug #8745)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>X11 hosts: fixed a problem of input focus cycles and immediately
           released key presses in full screen mode (bug #13238)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux hosts: fixed flooding the kernel log with USB related messages
           when passing through certain USB devices to a VM (bug #13085)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux guests: stop applications crashing when <emphasis>drm_wait_vblank</emphasis>
           is called (bug #13265)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux guests: fix a crash in gnome-session (bug #13335)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>X11 guests: do not start VBoxClient over an SSH connection
           (bug #13107)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>X11 guests: added support for X.Org Server 1.16 (bug #13207)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>X11 guests: fixed a wrong parameter in the video driver which
          caused problems with full-screen X11 clients (bug #2748)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VirtualKD: introduced stub/loader device for speeding up Windows
          kernel debugging, details see <ulink type=""
          url="http://virtualkd.sysprogs.org/">http://virtualkd.sysprogs.org/</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Version 4.3.14 (2014-07-15)</title>

    <para>This is a maintenance release. The following items were fixed and/or
      added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: more fixes for MSR emulation on certain hardware (bugs
          #12784, #12949, #13034)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: improve MSI handling under rare circumstances (only
          relevant for the ICH9 chipset)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed #UD exception for 64-bit guests with the EFER.SCE bit
          and the <emphasis>SYSCALL</emphasis> instruction (VT-x only;
          4.3 regression; bug #13008)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed timekeeping after resuming SMP guests</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: properly wake up a halted VCPU on NMI/SMI</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed a potential crash</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed stuck AltGr key on Windows hosts (bug #2537)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed a potential error during the version check</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: shortcut change should not require Enter/Return (or other
          trigger) to confirm (bugs #12828, #12847, #12937, #13087)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed update check which was broken due to changing the
          location of the root certificates (bug #13096)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxManage: fixed typo in <emphasis>showvminfo --machinereadable</emphasis>
          (bug #13176)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: fixed inbound half-close (bug #13116)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: fixed slow upload speed under certain conditions
          (bug #10034)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT Network: fixed potential loss of inbound TCP data</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT Network: fixed potential infinite stalls of TCP
          connections over IPv6</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT Network: fixed resets of TCP connections on Windows
          hosts</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT Network: fixed inbound half-close on Mac OS X hosts</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT Network: fixed socket leak on Solaris hosts</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT Network: fixed ping of mapped host loopback on Mac OS X
          and Solaris hosts, fixed proxying of IMCP errors on Mac OS X</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Host-Only Network: fixed SNMP <emphasis>ifConnectorPresent</emphasis>
          value on Windows (bug #13143)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed a possible crash with CD/DVD passthrough under
          certain circumstances</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed a crash when trying to open an inaccessible QED
          or QCOW image (bug #12613)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed data corruption or read errors under rare
          circumstances</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>AHCI: fixed a crash under rare circumstances</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>USB: performance fixes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ICH9: properly reset MSI capability on reset</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Keyboard: active modifier keys during suspend were stuck after
          resuming the host</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D: fixed misbehavior with huge guests (i.e. guest more than
          4GB guest memory</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D: several fixes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: properly detect the Windows 8.1 guest OS type (bug #13090)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ExtPack: cleanup of dangling uninstallation directories</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux hosts / guests: compile fix for EL7 (bug #12638)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux Additions: made 3D pass-through work with recent versions
          of Mesa in the guest (bug #12941)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux Additions: Linux 3.16 fixes (bug #13123)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X hosts: when scanning for host CD/DVD devices also consider
          BlueRay devices</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X hosts: fixed host shutdown and reboot delay caused by running VBoxSVC
          process in some cases</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>OS/2 Additions: fixed gengradd.dll library name (bug #12785)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Solaris Additions: fixed permissions of files and directories
        located on shared folders</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows host installer: fixed the need for rebooting Windows after
          installation or upgrade, extended logging for NetFlt/NetAdp (un)installation</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Version 4.3.12 (2014-05-16)</title>

    <para>This is a maintenance release. The following items were fixed and/or
      added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed an occasional Guru Meditation (Mac OS X hosts only;
          bugs #12727, #12954)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed a rare condition that would fail to invalidate guest TLB
          entries or would invalidate them when not required (Windows hosts only)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed a <emphasis>VERR_NOT_SUPPORTED</emphasis> Guru Meditation
          seen with certain guests, e.g. OpenServer 5.0.7</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: more fixes for MSR emulation on certain hardware (bugs #12240,
          #12875)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed mouse positioning with mouse integration disabled and
          multiple guest screens (Windows hosts only; bug #9059)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed crash in VM manager (bug #12878)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed crash under rare conditions on entering/exiting
          full-screen/seamless mode</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Shared Clipboard: don't stop working after taking a snapshot
          (bug #12700)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>AHCI: fixed a crash under rare circumstances</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: fixed a hang during VM shutdown under rare conditions</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: fixed generation of malformed ICMP error datagrams (4.3.10 regression)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: fixed potential crash in DNS proxy</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT Network: don't drop port forwarding rules after some time</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: fixed ARP cache corruption and network loss in Windows guest caused
          by iSCSI service activity</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>USB: improved check if a storage device is currently mounted to the host
          when the device is about to be attached to the VM (Mac OS X hosts only; #11038)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D support: several fixes, including better support for Ubuntu 14.04</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VRDP: fixed a potential crash on client disconnect (bug #12858)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxSVC: fixed a race when a new client is started a few seconds after
          the last client terminated (Windows hosts only; bugs #11309, #12509)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxSVC: fixed VirtualBox.xml registry corruption after VM renaming</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxSVC: fixed a potential crash caused by incorrect USB device filter
          (Mac OS X hosts only; #11038)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows hosts: partly support 32-bit COM on 64-bit systems</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows host installer: implemented merge module (msm) support</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux hosts: fixed dependency of boot script on older Debian systems
          (bug #12262)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux guests: fix symbolic link to shared folder helper
          (bug #12879)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux Additions: don't crash VBoxService during guest execute for
          users without a password (bug #12994)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux Additions: fixed a bug in guest execution where the guest process
          terminated with <emphasis>VERR_INTERRUPTED</emphasis> to the host</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Version 4.3.10 (2014-03-26)</title>

    <para>This is a maintenance release. The following items were fixed and/or
      added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: more work on improving the emulation of certain MSR registers
          on certain host CPUs (e.g. bugs #12734, #12736, #12744, #12748, #12686,
          #12770)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed single-stepping for real-mode guests (VT-x without
          unrestricted guest execution) and some I/O instructions (bug #12636)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed a potential problem with COW pages if nested paging is
          not available</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: Mac OS X: experimental native full screen support for
          Mountain Lion and Mavericks (bug #12292)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: Mac OS X: removed the mini-toolbar minimize button which
          doesn't work under Mac OS X full screen mode anyway</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: experimental HID LEDs synchronization for Windows and Mac OS X hosts:
          fixed keyboard re-synchronization if the feature is disabled (as done by default;
          bug #12758)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed a potential crash when opening the preferences menu
          (bug #12862)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>OVF: fixed a crash of the VirtualBox Manager when re-starting guest
          export (bug #12586)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D support: several fixes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>HGCM: fixed a problem with saved states which could cause several
          guest misbehavior after a VM was started from a saved state</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed a bug preventing to compact differential snapshots
        under certain conditions</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxSVC: fixed a segmentation fault on Linux hosts if a very long path
          exists under /dev (bug #12760)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: fixed guest misbehavior under certain conditions if a storage
          medium was attached or removed at VM runtime</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows installer: make the <emphasis>--silent</emphasis>
          parameter work again (bug #12764)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X Networking: prevent local traffic (VM-to/from-host) from
          leaking to wire (bug #12750)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions: fixed the environment for guest processes
          (4.3.8 regression; bug #12782)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions/WDDM: fixed divide by zero exception with
          multiple guest screens under certain conditions</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions/WDDM: fixed crashes with 2D video
          acceleration enabled (4.3.8 regression; bug #12745)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux Additions: install correctly on Ubuntu guest systems
           with a /usr/lib64 directory (bug #12513)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>X11 Additions: fix for the VBoxClient process not exiting
           correctly (bug #12348) and consuming too much processor time</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Version 4.3.8 (2014-02-25)</title>

    <para>This is a maintenance release. The following items were fixed and/or
      added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: more work on improving the emulation of certain MSR registers
          (e.g. bugs #12224, #12544)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed a <emphasis>VERR_INVALID_RPL</emphasis> Guru Meditation
          when booting certain guests (bug #11350)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: experimental support for SSE 4.1 / SSE 4.2 passthrough, see
          the user manual how to enable it (bug #8651)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fix for recent Linux kernels with software virtualization</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: experimental HID LEDs synchronization for Windows hosts, see
          <xref linkend="hidledssync" xreflabel="here"/></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: warn the user if the Oracle Extension Pack is not installed and
          the user tries to activate the remote display feature (bug #9104)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: make sure that a minimized guest (using mini toolbar in
          full screen / seamless mode) keeps the minimized state (bug #12199)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: popup banner's "do not show this message again" check-box
          replaced with corresponding button</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: network adapter cables can now be connected/disconnected directly through
          the running virtual machine Devices / Network menu a Network status-bar
          indicator</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: the new VM wizard now proposes 64-bit guests on 64-bit hosts
          by default; better distinction between 32-bit OS types 64-bit OS types
          (bug #12533)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: better error message if appliance import fails
          (bug #12657)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: allow to set host-combination to 'None' using the Global settings
          / Input page (bug #12730)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: don't switch the guest to a black screen during online snapshot
          merge (4.3 regression)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxManage: when exporting an appliance, support the suppression
           of MAC addresses, which means they will be always recreated on
           import, avoiding duplicate MAC addresses for VMs which are imported
           several times</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>AHCI: fixed a VM hang during suspend under certain circumstances</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>AHCI: fixed a VM hang during online snapshot merge under certain
          circumstances</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>AHCI: fixed a bug which resulted in Windows XP guest hangs if a
          SATA CDROM is attached (bug #12417)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>AHCI: fixed a Guru Meditation under certain conditions</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>AHCI: ejecting a CD/DVD medium failed under certain conditions</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>AHCI: disk hotplugging fixes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: transparent handling of host sleep/resume and network configuration
          changes if the dnsproxy is enabled or if the hostresolver is used
          (bug #12441)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: fixed crash and misbehaviour under some circumstances with
          ICMP packets having TTL=1</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT Network: fixed IPv6 reassembly</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT Network: ping proxy implemented</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>OVF: fixed reading of the OVF 0.9 section element
          (4.3 regression; bug #12345)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>OVF: several fixes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D support: several fixes, multiscreen fixes (e.g. bug #9124)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D support: include 3D content in captured videos (bug #12666)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D support: include 3D content in captured screenshot (bug #11758)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VGA: proper handling of legacy graphics modes if the Guest
          Additions are active (bug #6649)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>USB: fixed crash during isochronous transfer under rare
          circumstances</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>BIOS: better disk geometry handling of SCSI drives</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: fix crashes in Java API clients using the XPCOM binding,
           happened with output parameters only (bug #11232)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxSVC: documented the handling of host power management events
          (see <xref linkend="hostpowertweaks" xreflabel="here"/>) and
          added an extradata item for configuring the handling of the battery-low
          event (bug #9925)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxSVC: fixed a bug which could trigger a crash if a VM snapshot
          was restored the second time and the VM has associated bandwidth groups
          (bug #12569)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxSVC: properly detect ifconfig if located in <emphasis>/bin</emphasis>
          (bug #12713)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Shared Folders: fixed a failure to restore transient shared folders
         when starting a VM from a saved state (bug #12578)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X hosts: fixed issue when the application icon was frozen in
          the dock if the bridging interface was not connected to a network
          (bug #12241)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux hosts: also consider the physical package ID when determining
          the number of physical CPU cores</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux hosts / guests: don't warn in kernel log if memory allocation
          fails (bug #11171)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Solaris hosts: fixed the autostart SMF script (bug #11720)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows hosts: fixes for non-ANSI code page user names and similar
          environment contents (bug #12596)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows hosts / guests: fixed setting and using a guest user's process
          environment variables (relevant for Guest Control)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions: fixed handle leaks in VBoxTray (bug #12563)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions: fixed a crash while detecting active guest users</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions: fixed restoring backed up D3D files on
          XPDM -> WDDM upgrade</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Guest Control: fixed setting and using a guest user's process
          environment variables</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux Additions: support Enterprise Linux 6.5 kernels
          (bug #12505)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux Additions: fixed CPU hot-remove on newer Linux kernels</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux / Solaris Additions: don't automount a shared folder which is already
          mounted</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>X11 Additions: support X.Org Server 1.15 (bug #12623)</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Version 4.3.6 (2013-12-18)</title>

    <para>This is a maintenance release. The following items were fixed and/or
      added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed a Guru Meditation <emphasis>VINF_EM_TRIPLE_FAULT</emphasis>
          caused by VMCB caching with nested paging on certain AMD CPUs (bug #12451)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed a Guru Meditation <emphasis>VERR_VMX_UNEXPECTED_INTERRUPTION_EXIT_TYPE</emphasis>
          while intercepting debug exceptions (VT-x only; bug #12410)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed a Guru Meditation <emphasis>VERR_SVM_UNEXPECTED_EXIT</emphasis>
          while intercepting debug register accesses (AMD-V only; bug #12481)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed a <emphasis>VERR_SSM_STRUCTURE_MAGIC</emphasis> error when trying
          to load a saved state made with VBox 4.3.4 when VT-x/AMD-V is disabled. Unfortunately,
          VBox 4.3.4 produced broken saved states for this configuration so you have to discard
          these states (bug #12414)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: added a few more MSRs to the whitelist required by certain guests
          (bug #12245)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed deleting of inaccessible VMs (4.3 regression; bug
          #12205)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed warnings in VM settings / number of guest processors
          (bug #12480)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Main: don't automatically enable 64-bit guests on 64-bit hosts if
          VT-x/AMD-V is not available (bug #12424)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Main: always expose the DMI memory information to Windows 2012 guests
          (bug #12017)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Main: fixed occasional crashes on guest display resolution change
          (bug #7063)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Main: fixed reporting back temporary name when calling
          <emphasis>IGuestSession::DirectoryCreateTemp()</emphasis> (bug #12498)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: fix for a hang when launching a GUI VM through the API, which crashes
          due to GUI unavailability</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fix for <emphasis>BLKCACHE_IOERR</emphasis> runtime errors under
          rare circumstances (bug #11030)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Network: allow to start more than 5 PCNet instances (bug #12426)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>E1000: if the cable was disconnected before the guest initialized
          the device, the link status was not properly set to 'down' after the
          initialization completed despite the fact that there was no connection</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D support: fixed offset of guest 3D image elements (Mac OS X Retina
          hosts only; bug #11021)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Solaris hosts: fixed accessing the host driver from non-global zones
          (4.3 regression; bug #12271)</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Version 4.3.4 (2013-11-29)</title>

    <para>This is a maintenance release. The following items were fixed and/or
      added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fix for a bug in the Local APIC emulation causing a BSOD when
          booting certain guests (4.3.0 regression; bug #12240)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed loading of saved states if VT-x/AMD-V was disabled
          (4.3.2 regression; bug #12291)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed single-stepping inside the guest for certain
          instructions (VT-x only; bug #10947)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed a performance issue involving APIC accesses after rebooting
          a VM (4.3.0 regression; VT-x only; bug #12296)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed TPR patching to be enabled for 32-bit guests even when
          the chosen guest type is 64-bit (4.3.0 regression; AMD-V only)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed occasional <emphasis>VINF_EM_TRIPLE_FAULT</emphasis> errors on
          hosts without the unrestricted guest execution feature (bug #12198)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: don't bother the user with the BPP warning if no
          Guest Additions are installed</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed machine-window paint artifacts on VM reboot / guest-screen
          resize</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: make sure the assigned license and description are attached to
          the exported appliance</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed bugs in close VM action restrictions handling (bug #12333)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed incorrect wizards text colors for some unusual
          look and feel styles (bug #11743)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: should restore seamless mode as soon as possible after
          VM reboot or shutdown</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixes for medium enumeration</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: the OS X hot corners were not accessible while a VirtualBox VM
          is running (Mac OS X hosts only; bug #4139)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed an old bug which bared the host from cleanly shutdown / reboot
          if the VM selector window is open (Mac OS X hosts only; bug #8254)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Host-only Networking: fixed creating of host-only network interfaces
          (4.3.0 regression; bug #12182)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: don't run into an infinite loop in case the host cannot
          access any DNS server (4.3.0 regression; bug #12300)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: don't re-connect the cable if the DNS information changes
          and the cable was disconnected before (4.3.0 regression; bug #12225)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: fixed several issues with automatically starting /
          terminating of NAT networks on VM start / stop and configuration
          changes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxNetDHCP: don't block prevent VBoxSVC from terminating
          (bug #12264)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>2D Video acceleration: fix crashes on presentation mode switches
          (bug #9194)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>BusLogic: allow to run VMs with more than one BusLogic SCSI
          controller enabled</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Keyboard: fixed a VM crash if a VM was resumed from a saved state
          where at least one key was pressed (bug #11289)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxSVC: fixed a heap corruption under certain conditions (4.3.0
          regression)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxSVC: fixed a race leading to a hang during initialization
          (bug #12349)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>OVF: fixed import logic for OVF appliances containing multiple
          VMs</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>OVF: improved logic for finding an appropriate image format
          during OVF import</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: block the removal of the current snapshot if it has child
          snapshots (only relevant for VMs without snapshottable hard disks,
          their presence always prevented removal), which resulted in VM
          config corruption</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: mark VM configs with snapshots but without current snapshot
          as inaccessible, as this combination is nonsense</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: fixed information for some automatically generated events
          (only with XPCOM, Windows host was not affected), which caused
          errors when getting some of the attributes over the webservice
          (bug #12379)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>SDK: extended the functionality coverage for the C bindings</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Guest Control: various bugfixes and improved VBoxManage help
          (bugs #8072, #11044, #12336, #12338, #12346, #12371)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows hosts: another attempt to fix the massive DPC latency
          (bug #6242)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows host installer: make registering file extensions optional,
          contributed by Tal Aloni (bug #8009)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X hosts: properly sign the kernel extensions for Mavericks
          hosts (bug #12256)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X hosts: fixed a bug where the VirtualBox dock icon was
          not properly removed from the dock after a VM terminated preventing
          Mavericks hosts from shutting down (bug #12241)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X hosts: fixed minor installer issue (bug #12275)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux hosts / guests: Linux 3.13 compile fixes (bug #12358)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux guests: build the vboxvideo kernel module correctly on
           OL/RHEL 6.1 guests (bug #11996)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux guests: make 3D work on Slackware 14.1
           (bug #12320 comments 3 and 4)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Guest Additions/3D: fixed an occasional dead-lock (bug #12319)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions/3D: fixed possible memory leaking (bug #12228)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions/XPDM: use separate tables containing valid video
          modes for each virtual monitor</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions: fixed automatic logins for Vista and newer Windows
          guests (bug #12332)</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Version 4.3.2 (2013-11-01)</title>

    <para>This is a maintenance release. The following items were fixed and/or
      added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed restoring of the auxiliary TSC MSR in VT-x that caused host
          BSODs on Windows 8.1 hosts and unpredictable behavior on other hosts
          (bug #12237)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: provide fake values for a couple of MSRs to make more guests happy on
          certain hosts</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed detection of VT-x on certain machines where the BIOS would
          not set the VMX LOCK feature bit, which affected the VM settings in the GUI</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed TPR threshold which caused BSODs on Windows XP guests
           that use the I/O APIC (VT-x only; bug #12227)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed PATM saved state incompatibility for software virtualized
          VMs (bug #12222)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: don't fail if AMD-V isn't available if the VM is configured
          to use software virtualization</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed guest resize breakage on visual representation mode change
          (when switching from normal to full screen etc)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: make sure the guest screen is resized after restoring a VM from a
          saved state if the host screen size changed</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: disabled SCROLL LED sync from HID LEDs synchronization
          (Mac OS X hosts only)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Webcam passthrough improvements including GUI support (see
          <xref linkend="webcam-passthrough" />)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Guest Control: implemented more <computeroutput>IGuestSession</computeroutput>
          methods</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Guest Control: added support for deleting and renaming guest files + directories in
          VBoxManage</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Guest Control: various bugfixes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>API: incorrect handling of hardware UUID default value, resulting
          in an all zero DMI/SMBIOS UUID, which leads to Windows requesting
          re-activation (4.3 regression; bug #12244)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D support: fixed crash on shutdown if 2D video acceleration is enabled
          (Mac OS X hosts only)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D support: miscellaneous fixes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed detection of CD/DVD media when switching from an empty
          to a host drive with passthrough enabled</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed hang of the VM process when the disk is full under certain
          circumstances</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: listen for changes of NAT Network setting at runtime</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: NAT Network DHCP server now saves leases to a persistent
          storage</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Main: monitor changes in host DNS configuration</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X host: reworked a mechanism of adding a VM desktop alias
          from the VM selector</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X installer: remove old kernel extensions during upgrade
          (bug #12258)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux Additions: correctly set umask before installing
          (bug #12166)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>X11 Additions/3D: fix freezes starting 3D desktop (bug #11503,
           thank you Sam Spilsbury)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>X11 Additions/3D: fix depth buffer support (bug #11905)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>X11 Additions/3D: fix Age Of Empires 3 rendering (bug #11331)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions/3D: fix Google Earth plugin rendering</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions/WDDM: autoresize fixes</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Version 4.3.0 (2013-10-15)</title>

    <para>This is a major update. The following major new features
      were added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: major rewrite of the VT-x code and the AMD-V code including
          many bug fixes and performance improvements (for example bug #9659)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: introduced a lightweight instruction interpreter for
          situations not handled by hardware virtualization</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: extended messaging mechanism (new non-modal popup overlays
          used to show non-critical warnings and provide user with additional information)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: keyboard shortcuts management (input page of global preferences
          extended with possibility to edit general keyboard shortcuts for
          VirtualBox Manager and Virtual Machine)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: video capturing support (bug #4766)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Added USB touch device emulation</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Added experimental support for webcam passthrough
          complementing USB passthrough (see <xref linkend="webcam-passthrough" />)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Added SCSI CD-ROM emulation, including boot support</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VRDP: support for IPv6</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Guest Control: guest sessions now are running in dedicated, impersonated
          session processes (needs at least Guest Additions 4.3 installed)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Guest Control: implemented <computeroutput>IGuestFile</computeroutput>
          support</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>NAT: experimental virtual router mode: several VMs are
          attached to the same internal network and share one NAT
          service (see <xref linkend="network_nat_service" />)
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para>In addition, the following items were fixed and/or added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: significantly improved performance of NetWare 5.x/6.x
          guests on host systems without nested paging support</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: fixed losing host NMIs while in VT-x guest-context</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: changed order of actions in emulated task switch
          (bug #10532)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VMM: allow to activate VT-x while in SMX mode and provide more
          information if that is not possible</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: update check uses https</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: numerous minor internal cleanups and bug fixes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: HID LEDs synchronization when switching between guest window(s)
          and host (Mac OS X hosts only)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI, VBoxManage: when unregistering a VM, also unregister the
          hard disk images which are used exclusively (bug #10311)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: use the number of physical presented processor cores instead of
          the number of logical processor cores to check if the users assigned
          too many virtual CPUs to the guest</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Snapshots: made live snapshots work again (bug #9255)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Teleportation: made it work again (bug #9455)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: implemented AHA-154x compatibility mode in the
          emulated BusLogic SCSI HBA</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: significantly improved performance of large ATAPI PIO
          transfers (BeOS, Minix 3 guests affected)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: added floppy formatting emulation (NB: cannot be used
          to change existing media geometry)
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Settings: global and per-VM default frontend configuration,
          useful to select the use of alternative VM frontends</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Settings: limit depth of snapshot tree to 250 levels, as more
          will lead to decreased performance and may trigger crashes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Settings: the per-VM hwvirtextexcl setting has been replaced
          by a global hwvirtexclusive property</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Main: new event queue implementation which does not use the host's
          native event queue for processing VirtualBox events anymore</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Main: eliminate the use of SysV semaphores on all host OSes
           other than Windows, namely Linux, Solaris and Mac OS X, with the
           consequence that no system reconfiguration is needed to run more
           than approximately 100 VMs</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Main: use the XDG standard configuration folder instead of
           .VirtualBox on systems where it is appropriate (bug #5099)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Main: extension pack framework can now support loading HGCM
          modules, contributed by Jeff Westphal</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxManage: list more information about hard disk/DVD/floppy
          media, and support the <computeroutput>--long</computeroutput>
          option to show really all available details</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxManage: added support for optional command line parameters for
          the automatic Guest Additions update</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxManage: added support for listing active guest sessions, guest
          processes and/or guest files via
          <computeroutput>guestcontrol list &lt;all|sessions|processes|files&gt;</computeroutput>
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxManage: added support for closing active guest sessions via
          <computeroutput>guestcontrol session close --session-id &lt;ID&gt;|
            --session-name &lt;name or pattern&gt;|--all</computeroutput>
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxManage: added support for terminating active guest processes via
          <computeroutput>guestcontrol process kill|close|terminate --session-id &lt;ID&gt;|
            --session-name &lt;name or pattern&gt; &lt;PID&gt; ... &lt;PID n&gt;</computeroutput>
          or
          <computeroutput>guestcontrol [p[s]]kill --session-id &lt;ID&gt;|
            --session-name &lt;name or pattern&gt; &lt;PID&gt; ... &lt;PID n&gt;</computeroutput>
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxManage: added support for watching guest sessions via
          <computeroutput>guestcontrol watch</computeroutput>
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxManage: added <computeroutput>modifyvm --triplefaultreset</computeroutput>
          to make the VM reset on triple fault instead of triggering a Guru Meditation
          (see <xref linkend="vboxmanage-modifyvm"/>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D support: several fixes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>3D support: several fixes for Mac OS X hosts</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>OVF: several fixes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Extpack Installer: make it work if the file is located in a folder with
          special characters</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Keyboard: fix for reporting key sequences like Ctrl+Alt+Del
          for the USB keyboard emulation</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Shared Clipboard/X11: support for BMP-format images, contributed
          by Franois Revol</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X hosts: limited support for Mac OS X 10.9 (Mavericks)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Mac OS X hosts: use a launchd script instead of the deprecated
          StartupItem mechanism (bug #8940)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows hosts: don't cause massive DPC latency (only on certain
          hosts; still needs improving; bug #6242)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows hosts: consider symlinks when retrieving volume information
          (bug #11962)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows hosts: fixed an issue with USB2 devices being inaccessible
          when plugged into USB 3.0 ports</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions: fixed misbehavior with guest display
          power management (WDDM driver only; bug #11170)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions: fixed memory leak caused by WTSQuerySessionInformation()
          on Windows 2000 guests (bug #12072)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows Additions: ability to track guest user idle times through
          the newly introduced event <emphasis>IGuestUserStateChangedEvent</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux Additions: fixed udev detection in the init script
          with Linux 3.x kernels</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

</chapter>

