<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Release change log structure

Each release has a matching log of changes which were made for that and
earlier releases. Earlier releases means anything with a lower number (e.g.
5.0.18 is lower than 5.1.2) which was released before this one. The log is
kept in the file doc/manual/user_ChangeLogImpl.xml. Anything worth mentioning,
particularly new features and fixed bugs, with a trac bug number if possible,
should be added to the top of the change log (that is, the section for the
upcoming release) for the branch in which it first appears - stable or
development - before the next release. If you back-port it to older branches
please add an entry there too. When a new major release is made, change log
sections for earlier releases are merged in.

Change log sections are split into two groups: major new features (normally
only for dot zero releases) and fixes. In addition, the entries in each group
are ordered as follows:

    VMM-related entries (most important)
    GUI-related entries (most visible for users)
    Device-related entries
    VBoxManage/API/Main-related entries
    Host-related entries
    Guest-related entries
    BIOS/EFI/ACPI-related entries

Please do further ordering as seems appropriate by importance and visibility for
users, e.g. audio before serial ports and generally Windows before Linux.  Please
also try to describe the user impact, not the technical details, and only use
technical terms if no non-technical ones are clear enough.
-->
<chapter>

<!-- HACK ALERT! Seems we must have a single top level element for xi:include to work.
                           So, we use chapter and xpointer="xpointer(/chapter/)" with xi:include. -->

  <sect1>

    <title>Version 6.1.x (2020-xx-xx)</title>

    <para>This is a maintenance release. The following items were fixed and/or
      added:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Virtualization core: fixed a rare issue with ICEBP instruction
        causing guru meditations on Intel hosts (6.1.0 regression;
        bug #19171)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Virtualization core: fixed macOS Catalina guests failing to boot
          after upgrading to 10.15.2 onwards (bug #19188)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para></para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Version 6.1.2 (2020-01-14)</title>

    <para>
      This is a maintenance release. The following items were fixed and/or
      added:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>Virtualization core: fixed performance issue observed with
          Windows XP guests on AMD hosts (6.0.0 regression; bug #19152)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Virtualization core: consistent IBRS/IBPB CPUID feature
          reporting, avoids crash of NetBSD 9.0 RC1 installer (bug
          #19146)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: fixed updating of runtime info</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GUI: in Display settings, do not show "2D video acceleration"
          checkbox if it is meaningless for the selected graphics
          adapter</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Audio: fixed audio input handling when VRDE is enabled</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Audio: fixed crash in the HDA emulation when using multi-speaker
          configurations</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: fixed use of encrypted disks with snapshots involved
          (6.1.0 regression; bug #19160)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: improve performance of virtio-scsi</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Storage: read-only support for compressed clusters in QCOW2
          images</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows installer: include unintentionally dropped vbox-img.exe
          utility again</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows host: when installing or removing an extension pack,
          retry the sometimes failing directory renaming (usually caused by
          anti-virus software accessing the directory)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux host: Support Linux 5.5 (guest additions not yet)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows guest: accelerate 2D video decoding (scaling and color
          space conversion) if the VM is configured to use VBoxSVGA with 3D
          enabled</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows guest: fix guest additions installer to upgrade the mouse
          filter driver reliably</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Windows guest: when uninstalling older Guest Additions with old
          3D support enabled try restoring original Direct3D files</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux guest: improve resize and multi-monitor handling for VMs
          using VMSVGA (known remaining issue: do not disable a monitor
          "in the middle", causes confusion)</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Version 6.1.0 (2019-12-10)</title>

    <para>
      This is a major update. The following major new features were
      added:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Implemented support for importing a virtual machine from Oracle
          Cloud Infrastructure
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Extended support for exporting a virtual machine to Oracle
          Cloud Infrastructure, allowing the creation of multiple
          virtual machines without re-uploading. Also added option to
          export a VM to the cloud using the more efficient variant
          "paravirtialized", and to specify free-form tags for cloud
          images
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Virtualization core: Support for nested hardware-virtualization
          on Intel CPUs (starting with 5th generation Core i, codename
          Broadwell), so far tested only with guest running VirtualBox
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Graphics: New style 3D support (with VBoxSVGA and VMSVGA) remains,
          old style 3D support (with VBoxVGA) has been completely removed
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Shared Clipboard: Implemented experimental support for file transfers
          (Windows hosts/guests only at the moment). Needs to be enabled via
          VBoxManage (disabled by default).
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
        In addition, the following items were fixed and/or added:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Virtualization core: Drop recompiler, i.e. running VMs now needs
          a CPU supporting hardware virtualization
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Runtime: Works now on hosts with many CPUs (limit now 1024)
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Appliance and Cloud Import: Add field for defining firmware type (not
          part of OVF spec and thus manual in the Appliance case, for OCI it is
          automatically taken from the instance information)
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
            GUI: Improved the VISO creation and file manager dialogs
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GUI: Virtual machine list of VirtualBox Manager was improved. Machine
          groups are now more obvious visually and VM search functionality
          has been improved. Global Tools element can now be pinned in place,
          to avoid scrolling it with rest of machine list
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GUI: Virtual machine details pane is now extended with embedded editors
          for selected VM attributes, allowing user to edit them on-the-fly byi
          clicking corresponding hyper-links without opening VM settings dialog
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GUI: Details pane provides more complete information
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GUI: Internal medium enumeration routines were optimized to reduce the load
          and optimize the performance in cases when user have lots
          of media registered. Also, we again allowed to add existing media (and create new)
          via Virtual Media Manager
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GUI: More consistent medium selection (both showing known images
          and allowing to select using the file picker)
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GUI: VM storage settings page was adjusted a bit in usability regard. User is now
          allowed to change controller bus type and can move attachments between the controllers
          by using drag and drop
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GUI: Storage and Network settings pages bug-fixes and usability optimization
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GUI: Added a new soft (virtual) keyboard enabling arbitrary keyboard input to guests,
          including multimedia keys
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GUI: Fixed crash in cloud related wizards when accessibility
          functionality was enabled
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GUI: Show VM CPU load as part of status bar CPU indicator
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GUI: Improved and extended the Session Information dialog
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GUI: Fixed/improved mouse pointer scaling
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GUI: Some issues related to mouse integration cursor scaling were
          addressed (bug #14366), more to go
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GUI: Fix and unify geometry save/restore in various dialogs
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GUI: Added the missing restriction options for disabling new
          functionality such as the VISO creator
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          GUI: Popup messages mouse click fix
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Graphics: Remove 3D support for VBoxVGA (old one deprecated with 6.0)
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Graphics: Additional texture format support on Windows host
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Graphics: Improved fix for flickering on Windows host
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Input: Added support for horizontal scrolling in the PS/2 mouse
          device using the IntelliMouse Explorer protocol. Note that this support
          is automatically used by Linux guests but not by Windows guests
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>vboximg-mount: Experimental support for direct read-only access
          to NTFS, FAT and ext2/3/4 filesystems inside a disk image without
          the need for support on the host
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>vboximg-mount: Now also available on Linux host
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Storage: Experimental support for virtio-scsi, for both hard disks and
          optical drives (including boot support in BIOS)
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Storage: For optical drive emulation fix empty host drive crash
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          USB: Improvements for EHCI controller implementation
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          USB: Filter can now specify port path, uniquely identifying a port
          in a system
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          NAT: Fix TFTP OACK response, send only if request has options
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          NAT Network: Use non-blocking sockets on Linux for accepted
          incoming connections (port forwarding)
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          PCnet-ISA: Added new network adapter type, currently CLI only
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Audio: Allow changing the host audio backend while the VM is
          in saved state
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          ACPI: Report NVMe controller
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          VGA: Improve hardware and BIOS compatibility
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          VBoxSVGA/VMSVGA: Support YUV2 and related texture formats with hosts
          using OpenGL (macOS and Linux), which accelerates video playback
          when 3D is enabled by delegating the color space conversion to the
          host GPU
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          VBoxSVGA/VMSVGA: Several drawing fixes for the 3D case
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          VMSVGA 3D: Fixed OpenGL compressed textures
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          VBoxManage: More cloud functionality coverage, e.g. starting
          a cloud instance
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          VBoxManage: As part of the guest control feature support moving
          multiple source files/directories to a target directory
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Guest Control/VBoxManage: Added support for specifying multiple sources
          when renaming guest files
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxManage: Show "unrestricted guest" and "nested HW
        virtualization" CPU features when listing the host information</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          API: Reduce the amount of leftovers from Move VM function
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Shared Clipboard: Implemented experimental support for file transfers
          for Linux hosts on Windows guests (disabled by default)
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          SMBIOS: Store system UUID in little endian format which is the
          default for new VMs, while existing VMs stick to the old VirtualBox
          behavior of storing them in big endian format for backwards
          compatibility to avoid breaking the activation status of Windows VMs
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VBoxSDL frontend: Fixed running on Windows hosts</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          macOS host: Fix VM crashes (most visible on macOS Catalina)
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Linux host: Improve vboxweb systemd service dependency information
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Linux host: Drop PCI passthrough, the current code is too incomplete
          (cannot handle PCIe devices at all), i.e. not useful enough
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux host and guest: Support Linux 5.4 (bug #18945)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Linux host and guest: Force disabling of kernel module signing
        during build (user can do it afterwards)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Windows host: When possible, distinguish USB devices by port number; helps
          with accurate capturing of devices when multiple otherwise identical devices
          are connected
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Windows Guest Additions: Many fixes for drawing problems in the
          driver for VBoxSVGA
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Windows Guest Additions: Fixes for legacy VBoxVGA adapter, restore
          previously working cases
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Windows Guest Additions: Restore VHWA functionality for VBoxSVGA
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Windows guest: DXVA implementation for WDDM driver
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Documentation: Updated supported host operating systems, added few
          new manual pages (more to come later)
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          EFI: Switch to newer firmware code base and add NVRAM support,
          should improve compatibility with OSes significantly
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          EFI: Added support for booting from APFS
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          EFI: Added support for non-standard SATA and NVMe boot device paths
          created by OS X
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          EFI: Modified updated EFI code base to support older OS X guests again
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

</chapter>
